software engineering radio episode 67
roundtable and model travel development
and product lines
[Music]
welcome everybody to software
engineering radio this is the first time
we're actually recording a roundtable
discussion we are here isn't a
conference in Leipzig it's called what
is called product line and product line
engineering or something okay so it's
about monarch oh right there is I can
read this model driven development and
product lines synergies and experience
okay so and the nice thing about this
conference is that a number of experts
on those topics are actually here and so
I thought we have to get them together
and talk a little bit about some of the
topics but before we actually go ahead
and start the roundtable discussion I
want to remind you again of our pending
survey again we did get responses but we
will keep this open until we have at
least 500 responses we do want to get a
significant number of responses so we
have a statistical basis for for the
results so that they are significant
statistically and therefore please go
ahead if you didn't answer the survey
yet go to our website s e - radio net
click on the survey link and take the
survey it's only five minutes and you
can win a book Wiley has given us an
instance of the poza four book we've
opposed a five book we have so our books
we have the my book on model driven
development which fits the topic today
and and more so please go ahead take the
survey you're doing us a great favor
okay but now let's go ahead and
introduce the people in our roundtable
discussion you probably know my voice
since I've been on the podcast number of
times so I'm not going to introduce
myself so let's just start with
introduction my name is Europa Catalan I
come from company Mehta case and my
interest area on this topic is basically
metamodeling and building
domain-specific languages - out of
myself a development my name is Tomas
Tai I'm working at PNM informatics and
I'm interested in everything that has to
do with a process and
methods and there's one tool thing I'm
associated with it's open architecture
where something like the grandfather
people have heard about oaw a couple of
times we've had two or three episodes
talking about it so okay my name is
danila Borgia
I'm as a company called puresystems
and my mine interest is in software
product lines and how to get it done in
a new reality my name is axel
I am with sa P in a group called product
architecture and in that group my
responsibility is taking care of sa
piece design time tools and repository
I'm Willie a Schilling with the address
of a technology the company calls itself
the generator company hence my interest
is in any kind of generative programming
in automatic of software development
processes ok so let's get started on
some of the questions so let's start
with taking a look at the official world
of model driven development which is
more or less the stuff that the OMG
publishes OMGs MBAs then there are qvt
morphe these kinds of things so anybody
has any opinions about how relevant some
of these standards are probably some of
them are more relevant like morphe and
some of them are maybe not so relevant
anybody who wants to say something about
that maybe I can start with the first
comedy you thought saw that I would
comment on that one right yeah I have
followed the evolution of mouth starting
with version 1.4 and now we're in
version 2.0 if I'm not mistaken and I've
seen a lot of technical work going on at
the OMG and not all of that I have to
say was actually helping promote the
standard I think the OMG was kind of
trapped by IBM IBM forcing that split
into e Moff and seemed off upon the OMG
and the OMG just seemed to blindly
follow that then eventually IBM not
truly adopting even a moth when you look
at the current DMF implementation it is
not exactly compliant with what the mg
has with
and now eventually the the mah standard
has become kind of well it it's a big
split and it is very complicated to
implement nowadays doing a full mouth to
OC morph implementation now email for
general you're working on this right yes
we do mauve 1.4 we did take a close look
at math 2.0 because we thought some of
the things in math 2.0 might be of
interest to us then again some of the
things that we thought should have been
in especially when you look at UML 2
with its superstructure it would have
been so nice if they finally got it to
put the key qualifiers into the
associations also useful form off they
did not do it and and so we are stuck
kind with kind of with muff 1.4 which
was the last implementable but still
scalable version and I think the OMG has
not done itself a good service in
allowing for that split interesting to
hear that the people who make the
standards they don't follow it but
that's nothing new
basically it's good to have a standard
but only at the point of time when we
know what's working and as of today
there's clearly not a modeling language
yet for instance like UML which we would
not be working for model-based
development it's more like model-based
caching the same idea is with the xmi
the eczema has many versions and eczema
doesn't really work between two tools
earlier when we have other standards
like in 80s we had a PCT it didn't work
at 90s we had c-diff case data
interchange format it didn't work so it
doesn't surprise that xmi is not working
either it's good to have standards but
let's first make something which works
and then let's standardize and
unfortunately that's not the way how
long she works regarding XM i I agree
it's a mess that the OMG has created I
think it's partly due to the fact that
the OMG processes are lousy they don't
require you to do a reference
implementation and they don't require
compatibility and compliance testing now
that has been solved in a better way
with the JCP where the people are
required to publish test kits and and
stuff like that so do we have any
opinion on queue
the career of you transformation
standard is there anything happening
well I think that's a good example for
standard or tri-state to come out with a
standard which which has no practical
background because it is complete new
field and there there are so many topics
and in that area and I think when this
project started there nobody was able to
to really get the point what is good and
what is bad and what is appropriate and
I think the QUT standard which we can
read now exactly reflects this this
state there was no experience in model
model transformations when they did the
standard right so that if you find three
languages it's a good example of
carrying out research in a
standardization organization and what
you get is the mess that we currently
get it sounds like we were all
relatively skeptical about these things
is anybody there who wants to raise the
flag for the OMG and there no no just to
be fair the standards did have a good
effect on the development of the whole
field I think without math and it's
standardization we wouldn't be where we
are and also I think UML has helped a
long way so I would partly disagree that
you cannot do anything reasonable with
UML we at the company that I used to
work for before at interactive we did a
whole lot of very useful things with UML
and again that is well partly due to the
OMG well of course we know the three
amigos contributed that stuff to the OMG
and then well the critics would say then
the OMG kind of destroyed it afterwards
but so today during the conference I
noticed something which wasn't really
new to me but it became obvious I think
although this is a very relatively small
community we're in here all this
modeling and and generative and product
line stuff
I think the community isn't able to
agree on a common terminology for
example there are those different two
smart driven engineering model of an
architecture model runs off terrible
generative programming then people talk
about models DSL or metadata about
metamodels domain models or schemas then
there is all this technology stuff
Microsoft tooling you know versus
eclipse versus some of them are
proprietary solutions which sit next to
me so so do you think that that it's a
problem for the development of this
whole approach that the community
although it's small and it's it's
probably in its infancy it's already
splitting and can't even agree internal
I think some of the terms that you
mentioned do have a pretty well-defined
meaning it is just that some people tend
to confuse them constantly right the
question is what the cause root cause of
the problem is is it the unknowingness
of the people who just don't care about
the terminology and just use the terms
any way they like and so for example
when you mentioned DSL and metamodel of
course there is a clear distinction
between the two concepts like a meta
model just defines the abstract parts of
a syntax whereas a DSL is much more than
it so maybe it is more about the ways
that the terms are being used by well
let's say some of the not so literate
people so my impression is to some
degree is not only that people are
misunderstanding is that everybody is
misunderstanding it in a different way
so that makes things a little bit more
difficult even this morning you heard
we're talking about product families and
product lines and system families
sometimes there are unnecessary
distinctions just to say well this is a
very specific thing it needs a very
specific name and sometimes the the word
rings are overlapping and this max makes
it makes it more difficult to do voice
and the problem is is probably the
reason for it is probably that it is yet
not mainstream by any meaning and that
means there are a lot of people working
separately everybody has its own early
years and sometimes we meet in
conferences like this but we didn't have
a chance
to build a community and the community
where we can talk about these things and
we can build up a common wording
although cynically one could say that it
would be a useful thing for the OMG is a
standards body to make sure that these
terms are really properly defined but it
seems like they're doing other stuff
than you know it's I think it's partly
because we are relatively alone and go
out into the world discuss it with our
customers in some sense and it discuss
it in their terms and then we do things
which are not not ok and don't use the
exact term just to be able to talk to
the customers and then we meet and then
we have the problem that we use the
wrong terms even if we know if we would
think about it that we don't do the
right thing in the model driven world I
think we agree that round trip
engineering is typically not very useful
because the models are more abstract
than the code that's generated so there
is no easy mapping back from the code to
the models right right okay however
there is another initiative at the OMG
which and I think this is really funny
actually uses an acronym that has the
MDA letters reversed which is a DM which
is the architecture driven modernization
thing which is basically that's what I
understand a kind of model driven
reverse engineering so can somebody
explain what this is all about and how
it relates to MDA or or is that you know
I've always wondered about the the at
the back arrow from code into the model
in the NBA standard is it what's going
on there or what what about this ATM
stuff yes ATM is the wording is fine is
is just MBA but to understand that it is
it's not the exact idea that is we would
take software drop it into some kind of
machine and out out comes some UML code
that's not exactly the idea the idea is
though the wording gives the impression
the idea is to use make some kinds of
mechanisms to understand the
applications just to understand existing
let's say legacy application
to understand what is in there in the
application what are the functionalities
what are the assets and so on in several
areas and several directions is it is at
least not up today there are no nobody's
trying to automatically derive models in
like like a UML model there are standard
models to express what is in the
applicator in the applications but not
just in automatic transformation I can't
imagine it today an automatic
transformation from let's say an
existing COBOL application one hundred
twenty thousand lines of code I've seen
things like that into just one uml model
is without any use but it is useful to
understand the application is useful to
express what you understood in agreed
models that's that's the idea so sorry
it is to standardize certain metamodels
that that that that allow people to
express software structures yes and to
allow to well again the idea is that
allows two vendors to exchange the what
they found out there are some who are
specialists and let's say discover
things and then x1 do one analyze route
and so on I know this I know this this
comes back to the question how useful a
6m I to exchange these informations but
we had the answer for that before
sounds like an OMG because the issues of
program understanding or architectural
recovery they are tough Academical
research questions today they are not at
all at the state of being standardized
but the gain doesn't surprise me well I
have another view in it because there
are already lots of tools out there in
the market and it's a necessary task so
we cannot wait until the you know in the
research all the questions are answer
for that because when there are answered
nobody isn't any more interested in this
at this answer so it might be it might
be useful it might be useful too
let's see at least
it is smallest common denominator to
find out what are the informations we
can share and we can exchange without us
and in practice we're doing it already
we're doing it with another company they
have analyzers tools and transformations
to other languages and we have some
analyzers and discovery tools for
existing applications a bit it looks
useful as long you know I'm afraid I'm
afraid is the usual process is that more
and more requirements are added more and
more functionality is added to the
models until they are not useful anymore
that's it that's a risk but up today it
looks like really some something useful
it is completely based on more and only
more not UML it but producing UML so
these meta models are comparable to what
the CWM metamodel does for data
description exactly is this a similar
approach and it's overlapping the data
description part of C WMS is used within
a DM and we also agree as a community
here that this is something different
than what we talked about the model
development and MBA it's it's not just
simply the way back for a roundtrip
engineering it's really kind of a
digging in in the dirt in the
architectural and in the systems to find
out what they're all about right what is
exactly the difference between MDA and
ADM if you have in in both areas you
have meter models domain-specific
describing architectural things or more
business related things and there's not
the intention to have roundtrip
engineering so what's exactly the
difference it's more intentional and
than formal right one difference is
where you start right you start with the
model or you start with the code that's
the difference you start with the code
and you cannot expect the code to be let
for instance to be well designed well
architectures you don't know for
instance you don't have things like
classes in existing COBOL applications
and and so on so you have you're dealing
with different artifacts you're dealing
with different model elements
you can't try to translate them after
what transform them into UML more
elements but it's e to some degree it's
a different world at least in the
beginning yes but if you have say DSL
which describes those things then you
can perfectly use it to describe not
only legacy applications but to design
new applications as well or don't you
expect that I'm not a contradiction
about that that that's a different
approach it's a different approach years
approach to try to standardize the model
to be able to exchange the data about
the applications that's it that a
different approach starting with the
earth ESL's can help and will help I
know and to some degree we are doing
exactly that way we're not using we're
not waiting until a DM is completely
specify 25 we say the truth we using the
things that we think that are usable
similar as we were before was more for
you for instance we're using still the
autumn of 1.4 words we employ using this
buona notte release 2 and on the ATM
side what we have like I think in the
end like every other tool builder we're
picking those elements that look to be
useful and it helps us just keeps to
invent from inventing those things
ourselves so this conference is called
product lands in multiple developments
symmetries so what are these synergies
is model driven development basically
the same thing as product lines does it
make sense to use model driven
development for one up applications if
you don't do para and product lines or
the other way around is it today useful
to do product line engineering without
doing model driven development and
formal modeling where do we think other
synergies there probably to most of your
questions the answer is yes
it is it is a my opinion that you and it
has been proved and you can do obviously
software product lines without yeah
that's why I said today model different
development and you will probably do it
in certain domains still in ten years
there are we can probably agree on this
or maybe we can agree on this that there
will be parts of the of the whole a
computer scientific domain where there
where models are not that useful and
there will probably an overlap between
software product line domain and those
domain the the reason why I'm asking is
because whenever we talk about product
lines you're one of the first people to
mention that it's important to formally
and I was pointing at tenido by the way
when I said you can't see that on the
podcast so and so you're one of the
first to point out that it's important
to formally describe the variabilities
between the different products in the
product line and these descriptions are
models so you could easily argue that
this is a form of modern urban
development where the models aren't
structural like UML or or or some other
graphs basically but rather the model is
a configuration of a future model so in
that sense maybe yeah well actually what
what we try to teach our customers is to
do as much formalization as possible in
in the given context and one of the
important things in the software product
line area is to model the variability
and we try to make them use formalisms
for this but there are other parts
usually the implementation part is in in
many cases not not formalized able in a
model since we have legacy components
and it doesn't really make sense in for
very small applications to build a
generator often and software product
lines are on the other hand often where
a lot of many similar small applications
well the synergy between md st and and
product line engineering i think there's
a an overlap in process or could be
a useful overlap in process this domain
engineering and application engineering
for example stuff exactly and okay one
can live with without the other I think
we all agree about that I think what
what Marco's said is is right that MDS D
is an abstract concept which covers the
concept of feature modeling and variants
in in some way
there might be one subtle difference
though I mean when I look at what SI p
does with its 30,000 roughly
configurations which is we have in our
business suite imagine how many
combinations that results in its its
vast and when I look at the processes
and the ways how that is developed we
heard it in one of the talks today that
those are mainly configuration tables so
eventually what happens is you have a
very lean UI that just helps you add
configuration time which is not designed
time and thus fundamentally different
from the processes we use in model
driven development so a configurator or
a consultant working during the
implementation phase at a customer will
set those configuration switches which
map directly into a configuration table
no code will be changed
there will be no generation step there
will be nothing except that an if will
take another route in the code so that I
think is a is a difference maybe not so
subtle when I think about it maybe even
more fundamental between the model
driven development processes and and
tooling that we observe and the ways
that configurations of product lines
sometimes work one clear way where
models make sense in a product lines is
that if you want to raise the
abstraction higher because today the
variability is very difficult to
maintain the code and models are all
filled way to do that and it's very
known principle already from 80's to
build domain-specific languages then
they were more textual ones which then
describe only what is it different among
family members and then tied with the
code generator then you would also
produce new kind of functionality not
just
aggressions but you can also build
totally new kind of applications that
didn't exist anymore or before that so
one of the reasons I was asking is
because if you talk to ple people
product line people then they typically
talk about configuration models it's
basically this feature modeling stuff
and if you talk to model driven
development folks they talk about things
like UML or other graphical or textual
languages so the the ple stuff is more
the configuration kind of thing whereas
the model driven people more have this
creative construction approach to use
the two terms that question of
charnetski at some point introduced
where you creatively build something
from a set of primitives defined in a
meta model so I I kind of don't see
necessarily how I mean the two
communities just have a different focus
but you can still do model development
with future models or product line
engineering with structural models so
that's why I was asking it it seems
these things are a little bit they have
different backgrounds or different I
think that the in my opinion model
driven development this is one of the
very good ways to implement software
product lines much more efficient than
we do today and the on the other hand
the configuration models which we have
talked about an integral part of the
software product line development not
only on the technical issue on a
technical side but also for the
management of the whole lifecycle of an
application development and software
product land developers much more than
configuration it's it's about how you
get the information how we were used
information throughout the development
process and that's the difference model
driven development is somehow a
relatively technical thing and most of
the problems in software product and
development are basically only
management issues are management issues
and so there is an big overlap any
technical technical things and then we
have other things in software product
line which are actually more of a
problem than the technical configuration
one clear distinction that I see among
people who do configuration and those
who use domain-specific languages to
make variants is that are the
applications already available during
the production
in people who do configurations they
expect that all the variants are already
available implementation code is
available and then the code is combined
with the configurations that is fine and
works in some areas then there are other
areas where you can't expect that the
code is already available and you can
build a domain-specific language on top
of the platform and then you can also
make new functionality not just the
configuration but you can actually make
new code from the models my feeling is
just talking about model driven is too
indifferent you know model driven you
have to understand first in which
direction they're stretching ghosts in
your model so there are mortal driven
approach is based on UML which is
completely different approach than a
model driven development based on future
models so they're orthogonal this
concept or something like
domain-specific languages and that's
that's that's one of the problems we had
in the right in the beginning what does
the word mean and probably need new
words so we have to be clear about that
yeah that's a new terminology we have to
be serious about that I had a
presentation some month ago in Italy and
we're talking about the model driven
approach and after talking one hour and
explaining what what can be done on what
we're doing there was a question well
and where are the UML diagrams yeah
that's probably because of my English oh
they are understanding of English I
don't know you can you can have the same
thing if you go into automotive domain
model model based development they call
it is identical to saying we use a
specific product called MATLAB Simulink
and and right Aetna took me a while to
understand so do we have any opinions as
a group on what's more useful textual or
graphical to yourselves or are there any
sweet spots for either of them I think
you have picker I think you have an
opinion there they don't need to only be
in
my mind says textual or graphical they
can be also table based or matrixes and
the representational form and the
notation so to speak should be selected
on what feels most natural in that
application area if the developers feel
that text is fine then they should build
a domain-specific language based on text
if they see that they need to see a
inter connections between elements and
they want to use matrixes then the
domain-specific language should be based
on matrix or graphical one like many of
them are just it's a choice of the
person who defines the language I would
also agree that a lot of personal
preferences of the modelers or
developers or whatever you call them is
involved I think in addition to that we
can see that text based is still a lot
better understood than graphical
modeling when you think about those
tougher problems like how to merge those
models or what happens in case of
changes in the abstract pieces of the
model how do you have to adapt the
graphical representation and those he's
longing for the mic I think we
understand that better today for
text-based stuff that doesn't
necessarily mean that we were never
gonna get it for the graphical stuff in
index based development we have horrible
problems with versioning having the same
files and and copied the same text in
multiple places and it's very horrible
but people who get used to that that's
the way of living if I change my heater
file goodbye my I need to remember that
to change also my C file so people have
used that they are inconsistent then
then there's no problem with the text
although I've never seen that in Java
but I think copy and paste of course
could also happen with graphical models
I think there is there for me there is a
again this basic misunderstanding for
the model a model is not just some boxes
drawn at lines between it that's not a
model although everybody thinks models
have to be boxes and lines and things
like that models can be text as well the
model is what is in a metadata and boxes
at lines and text our
presentations of that are renderings
obviously here there are renderings and
so the discussion is a little bit
misleading whether it should be boxes or
tacks I agree but concrete syntax
matters as well for economical from an
economical point of view because it's
it's not the same for people if they if
they write text or if they they have a
graphical representation in a good
argument to that point that concrete
syntax does matter is the lack of
success of the UML action semantics
which might have been caused by the lack
of a concrete syntax for it
so maybe let's briefly visit another
topic which is today's tools for
modeling some of them I mean there are
several issues one is of course the
usability of some of the tools to build
editors some of them are not that great
others are maybe better I mean looking
at somebody and then there is maybe the
scalability of some of the underlying
infrastructure which is an interesting
topic for example if you look at EMF and
you have all those XML or XML files
which reference each other by various
more or less you know scalable and
robust means then the question is how do
you how can you actually build an
enterprise-wide modeling infrastructure
so I think this is an interesting topic
so who wants to say something first
we had s AP are trying to do that it
might well be that we are proven wrong
and then I have to say we didn't know
how to do it but the way we think how it
can be done is starting out with the
repository aspects first so not handle
all the problems at once I think of a
reasonable scalable model to use our
capable repository is key to success in
that area I presented today a couple of
the features that it has to have then on
top of that you have to have all the
various services including tool building
support and reasonable frameworks and I
think standards do not matter so much it
has to be easy and and I completely
agree with other tool builders on the
table on there
on that issue today we have a
presentation from Porsche on building
domain-specific languages and generating
HMI and even though they generate the
HMI and can execute it the people still
would like to use a PowerPoint because
that's what they have used to so clearly
if you want to use some structure or
formalism we are forcing people to to
use some other tools than the PowerPoint
but I guess as a task for two-level
overseas then trying to make the
modeling functionality looking as easy
as a PowerPoint could be yeah but that's
a horrible idea there was this this
other joke going around when people
talked about executable UML which is
stripped down to have very precise
semantics that the next evolution would
be executive UML which is basically a
PowerPoint profile which has absolutely
no semantics actually I'm curious to see
what what will come along when we have
the what's it called smart documents
with office 12 what's that what it gives
you as far as I understood it a
colleague of mine presented the ideas to
me as far as I understood it you can
have specific XML bridges to underlying
XML documents and you can link those
things to the elements in your office
documents so for example you can set up
a PowerPoint frame and then have
specific elements in the presentation
that relate to data coming from the
outside and I was thinking that could be
a way of using that as a tool front end
yeah okay I have two two more questions
and I think then we have to go because
there is some social event or party this
evening which we probably shouldn't miss
so one is MVD and offshoring I've always
argued and also in some of the previous
podcast episodes that if you do MDD
right then there is no economic benefit
in offshoring because you can get the
same improvement in or the same reduce
reduce meant in the amount of money you
have to spend basically it's going to
get cheaper so any opinion there any
experience there may be where we can say
that offshoring can be you know we don't
have to offshore and rather do modern
development any opinion
I can also cut out the question if
nobody's answering I've seen that some
people use model driven development as
an argument for offshoring they say we
can ship the models then to somewhere
else and then people there can use tools
to they press the button then they press
button basically well that means that
they have to do less work and it can be
better controlled I don't buy into that
vision in the first place I think it is
it is off by far I think there is a lot
of other issues in in offshoring we as a
PR experiment I would call it
experimenting with it you know that we
have labs all over the world Israel in
Bangalore India we have labs in China
there I wouldn't think that whether or
not you might have changes anything in
the fundamental aspects of the game
executives to perceive the cost
difference the well as I said they
perceive it it's a seeming cost
difference that doesn't really exist if
you ask me there is all kinds of risks
involved in offshoring and and
difficulties and modeling doesn't
doesn't influence that significantly I
think I don't know whether there's real
experience with offshoring your new
showing and and model different software
development but what we observe is that
there is a kind of movement into that
direction and movement for offshoring
and a movement for using model driven
things to to build a kind of frame for
our safety safety net for offshoring we
have no experience if this is practical
or not but I think we all have to deal
with the with the market and with the
market aspects and offshoring is a theme
that is present on the market and maybe
model driven development can be in
created in an offshore scenario so what
would be the way I mean our analysts
draw the models and and the offshore
folks implement the generator or do we
implement the generator because we want
to standardize our architecture and then
they draw the model based on Word
documents or or are they literally just
going to press the button which is
obviously stupid because it doesn't
matter where I press the button so I
mean what would be the way I think
people are fighting over the microphone
and so I won't okay
well one major argument for offshoring
is the the cost of the people in other
parts of the industry there is a good
answer to that if we don't try to move
the move the the factory steer to
another country we start to automate our
processes so I think that's a new idea
for for software developer Berkeley but
something we should consider is do to
add more automation into development and
MDD can be part of this idea about part
of the solution for that
I cannot imagine it's a completely non
complete London see use motor driven
development to do it offshore so what is
the use of that just to quickly reply to
that it I think it depends on the way
you do your model driven setup if you
can if you can completely generate the
applications out of the models I would
completely agree there is no sense and
somehow trying to combine that with
offshoring it's exactly like automating
production intensive processes in other
parts of the industry or our other
industries however what I have seen in
several cases is that there is need to
refine the products of the generation
steps or the model transformation steps
and in those cases the question remains
who does those things and I think there
is reason in trying to offshore those
parts of the process having the
specifications of the models in the
high-cost locations and then trying to
offshore the refinement to lower cost
locations okay last question before we
wrap up today so we're here in this
model driven and product lines
conference you know there are about 100
participants
something so some people say that's
because we're in some remote part of
Germany because that so few people are
here but that's of course cynical the
question is how how widely spread how
well adopted is all this model driven
and product line stuff really
I mean is it mainstream already how fast
is it becoming mainstream we carried a
last month market survey in
german-speaking Europe and 70% of the
interviewed people who made product line
who made products new model based
development approaches like
domain-specific modeling or visual
studio team system modeling tools
digital tools or Eclipse modelling
framework so 70% people know not so many
are using it so there is something to do
but the knowledge is there and
increasing number of companies are
starting to move them and considering to
use them so clearly there are steps to
be take steps to to to be taken and
still so are we happy is it being
adopted fast enough I mean after the
initial MDA hype things have I think my
feeling is that things have slowed down
considerably that it's not you know the
adoption of model driven stuff is not as
fast as people could have thought isn't
it clear UML is now 10 years old and it
hasn't delivered the promise is it gave
so of course people are skeptical what
about the more product line oriented
things Daniel I have a PowerPoint slide
which I adjust every year which has two
hours once a timeline and one is the use
of for our clients and I I while I
adjusted one by by centimeter each each
year to extend the timeline but you
don't change anything about I just put
it I just put it a little bit closer to
where I where I say everybody knows at
least about it and there's that as an
emerging use of these technologies in
where should should be
used in the first place five years ago
nobody was talking about and and now I
we are able to talk about these problems
and we finally get some some companies
to see that there are already solutions
to some of the problems they have so I
guess there has been some progress and I
feel at the last five years were quite
important in this area but although it's
funny because for example EMG still
didn't include future modeling into the
the URL which would be terribly useful
and they didn't do it so at least the
main ok we're again at this oMG thing
but I was just saying that they didn't
include it ok there was no there was no
opinion there well if the thing is that
this kind of modeling is something which
also other standardization bodies failed
to do if you look at Auto saw a
standardization among automotive
software development companies they had
a working group for exactly this thing
and after two years ago simply gave up
and said we can't do it I think it the
model driven business has caught on
quite a bit a lot of people in the
environment that I see are using it in
one way or another
si P as I show today is using it big
time the true problem is the
heterogeneity due to the absence of
working standards probably so if you see
that proliferation of tools and and
technologies and frameworks and
workbench environments and whatnot and
the problem is the things don't really
get fit together in a way that it
becomes industrial industrially viable
in a big scope let's say and I think we
have to get get that changed you know
one final comment our observation there
recently a world famous as they put it
modeling tool vendor released a new
modeling tool and what they can do
basically is they can do class diagrams
you have our class diagrams and their
primary sales argument is they can do
round-trip engineering so you know again
this class picture to class code which
is as we all agree probably useless more
or less completely so either the company
didn't get it or which i think is more
more likely they advertise with this
round-trip engineering because people
want to have it so people didn't get it
so so didn't weren't we able to yeah at
the second one so the world we were able
to to you know to transport the message
our people still on this round-trip
class diagram to class file level that
is the together problem that you
mentioned the that address to that
address to pain points at once and they
did it in an appropriate way killing
those two pains the one pain was that
executives kept asking for diagrams
trying to explain what the architecture
or the design looks like and developers
hated to use UML tools so they together
killed both pain points at once
developers could continue writing code
and then on a press of a button produce
the diagrams and the executives would
just shut up this is kind of an mortal
alibi by bundling it's just just like in
the past when we when C++ was introduced
all of a sudden every C program was an
object-oriented programmer because it
had the plus plus in the name and you
could have done class this is just this
a beauty take just a piece of Java code
drop it into intuitive smashing and you
get you get nice pictures so you have a
model so you're doing modeling and you
know looking a little bit back some we
had this this flowchart diagram machines
taking some coke or something like that
drawing flowchart exactly the same that
is for all those people that don't like
you don't like to use models they will
use these tools that's about a reverse
engineering was already there no it's
not a reversing okay it's a
visualization of code structures yeah
but it's just just only to have
something to period yeah you have
something to pin it to the superior data
board that's the idea behind you could
say well we're doing modeling which by
the way goes to show they're in some
cases graphics
help they help understanding structure
but I remember having worked with
plus J or sniff plus when was that like
probably 1012 years ago or so and it was
great for visualizing inheritance
hierarchies and everything it we never
called it a modeling tool but it was
just helpful I think that's the way the
mentioned to provider sees their
development I didn't mention any tool
provided by the way I didn't say
together and - okay so then thanks
everybody and we have fun tonight bye
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio dotnet
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning poly for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the software engineering
radio website for details